# YADOK BIPLANG GODWILL

Pukekohe, Auckland 2677 | Mobile: +64220705531 | Email: biplang2006@gmail.com

LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/biplang-yadok

## **SUMMARY**

I am interested in becoming a significant scientific contributor in ecosystem conservation and the study of forest dynamics. I have a background experience in surveying wood species in tropical forests, zoochorous seed dispersal and exploring tree phenology data in relation to climatic variables.

#### **EDUCATION**

## PhD (Ecology), University of Canterbury, New Zealand. 2015–2018

Thesis title: Aspects of the behaviour of the African giant pouched rats (*Cricetomys* sp. nov) in relation to its seed dispersal potential in a West African montane forest landscape

## MSc (Conservation Biology), University of Jos, Nigeria. 2011-2013

Thesis title: Habitat selection and Territory size of the Northern Anteater-chat (*Mymecochla aiethiops*) in surrounding areas of Amurum Forest Reserve, Jos-Plateau, Nigeria

## BSc (Zoology), University of Jos, Nigeria. 2004-2009

Thesis title: Diversity and abundance of fig wasp species in *Ficus abutilifolia* and *Ficus thonningii* in Amurum forest reserve

## **PUBLICATIONS**

**Yadok B. G.**, Gerhard D., Forget P-M., Aliyu B. & Chapman H. M. (**2020**). Seed nutrient content rather than seed size influences seed dispersal by scatterhoarding rodents in a West African montane forest. *Journal of Tropical Ecology*, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0266467420000127">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0266467420000127</a>

**Yadok B. G.**, Pech R. & Chapman H. M. (**2019**). Perception of predation risk by Arican giant pouched rats (Cricetomys sp. nov) is higher in forest-edge microhabitats. *Behavioural processes*, **168**: 103953

Charles L, Dwyer J. D., Chapman H. M., **Yadok B. G** & Mayfield M. M. (**2019**). Landscape structure mediates zoochorous-dispersed seed rain under isolated pasture trees across distinct tropical regions. *Landscape Ecology*, 34 (6): 1347-1362.

**Yadok B. G.**, Gerhard D., Forget P-M. & Chapman H. M. (**2019**). Low fruit-crop years of *Carapa oreophila* drive increased seed removal and predation by scatterhoarding rodents in a West African forest. *Acta oecologica*, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.actao.2019.103448

**Yadok B. G.**, Gerhard D., Forget P-M. & Chapman H. M. (**2018**). Size doesn't matter: Larger *Carapa* seeds are not dispersed farther by African rodent community. *African Journal of Ecology*. 56: 1028-1033.

**Yadok B. G.**, Barshep Y. & Cresswell W. (**2014**). The importance of anthropogenic effects in habitat use and territory size of Northern Anteater-chats (*Myecocichla aiethiops*) near Amurum Forest Reserve, Jos-Platea, Nigeria. *Ostrich* 85: 147-151.

**Yadok B. G.** & Georgina Mwansat **(2009)**. Diveristy of fig wasps species in *Ficus abutilifolia* and *Ficus thoningii* in Amurum forest reserve, Jos-East, Nigeria. African journal of Applied *Zoology and Environmental Biology*. 11: 93-100

### **SUBMITTED ARTICLE**

Jaafar, R., **Yadok B. G**., Elisha, E. & Chapman H. M. (**2021**). The value of Isolated grassland tree species and the common bulbul (Pynonotus barbatus) in re-establishment of Afromontane forest into grassland. Submitted to *Biotropica* 

### **MEDIA PRESENCE**

Abengowe E. C., Adeyanju T. E., Akiemien N., Albert M. T., Azi, A. J., Elke F., Nwaogu C. J., Onoja J. D. & **Yadok B. G**. (**2011**). Amurum forest reserve habitat and avifauna mapping in Nigeria. <a href="https://www.qgis.org/en/community/qgis-case-studies/plateau-state-nigeria.html">www.qgis.org/en/community/qgis-case-studies/plateau-state-nigeria.html</a>

University of Canterbury Research Reports (2017) Rats to the rescue in African montane forests <a href="https://www.canterbury.ac.nz/media/documents/research/research-reports/Research\_Report\_2017.pdf">https://www.canterbury.ac.nz/media/documents/research/research-reports/Research\_Report\_2017.pdf</a> (pages 16 and 17).

# AWARDS/ACHIEVEMENTS/RECOGNITIONS

2019: Elected as West Africa coordinator of the ATBC Africa Chapter Committee

**2018:** PhD Study featured in the 2018 annual research reports of the University of Canterbury

2015—2017: T. Y. Danjuma PhD Scholarship (Full)

**2015**: Carolina MacGillavry award for best collaborative grant proposal, International Foundation of Science (IFS), Team INVAFRICA

2013: Completed Msc program with a Distinction 2013

**2011-2013**: A. P. Leventis full scholarship for Msc students in Conservation biology in at the University of Jos, Nigeria

# **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Proficient in analysing data using R, QGIS, Density, and Microsoft office programs.

Designing experiments and testing hypothesis.

Identification and survey of wood species in tropical forests.

Field navigation and appropriate use of field gear.

### **COMMUNICATION SKILLS**

Interpersonal communication: Excellent communication via written/verbal means with non-scientific and scientific audiences.

Audio-visual: Effectively communicate my findings via graphical, video and photographic means. Competent with the use of Microsoft PowerPoint and photo/video editing software.

### **RELEVANT EXPERIENCE**

## Ecologist (Te Whangai Trust, Miranda, Waikato, New Zealand, June 2020 till date):

Assessed sites for native tree planting, provided ecological impact assessment for intended projects, prepared biosecurity plans and participated in strategic meetings with city and regional councils.

Research Assistant (University of Canterbury, New Zealand, Fixed-term September 2019 – May 2020): Data entry and organization (collected data from Ngel Nyaki forest reserve), data analyses, report writing, managing collaboration meetings writing scientific papers.

Academic Support staff; part time (University of Canterbury, New Zealand, February 2017

- August 2019): Assisted in teaching undergraduate students (Diversity of life; BIOL 113) Data entry and organization (collected data from Ngel Nyaki forest reserve).

Research Associate (A. P. Leventis Ornithological Research Institute, Nigeria, January 2014

- January 2015): Wildlife surveys of behaviour and distribution of vertebrate animals and insects in Ngel Nyaki forest reserve. Live trapping and marking of birds and rodents. Experimental design of bird and mammal surveys. Analysed collected data and prepared reports for the field station.

**Pioneer Science Coordinator (Nigerian Montane Forest Project, Nigeria, 2013):** Planning (roasters) and supervision of scientific projects being carried out at Ngel Nyaki forest reserve. Organised a proper storage system of plant and animal samples/tissues in the herbarium.

## Intern at A. P. Leventis Ornithological Research Institute, Nigeria, 2008.

Bird identification and observation, bird trapping and handling, body condition monitoring of re-trapped birds, and insect sampling. Sampling and identification of insects collected from forest fruits.

## SELECTED WORKSHOP, CONFERENCES AND SEMINAR

**2019**: Participated in the 2019 Centre for Tropical Forest Science ForestGEO (Smithsonian Tropical Forest Research Institute) analytical workshop and training at Nanyang Technological University, Singapore.

**2019**: Presented a seminar about my PhD in the Faculty of Agriculture and life Sciences, Lincoln, University, Canterbury, New Zealand.

**2018**: Presented a talk at the Australasian Society for the Study of Animal Behaviour (ASSAB) in Brisbane, Australia.

**2018**: Presented a talk at the Association of Tropical Biology and Conservation (ATBC) in Kuching, Malaysia.

**2017**: Presented a talk at the Association of Tropical Biology and Conservation (ATBC) in Merida, Mexico

#### **REVIEWER EXPERIENCES**

**2020:** Scientific article for the *Forest Systems* journal, Spain.

2018: Student research grant application reviewer, Animal Behaviour Society (ABS), USA

**2018**: Scientific committee member, Association of Tropical Biology and Conservation (ATBC) conference in Kuching, Malaysia

**2017**: Abstract review committee member, Annual Biology Conference (ABC), University of Canterbury, New Zealand

#### SELECTED RESEARCH GRANT AWARDS

**2018**: American Society of Mammalogists (ASM), African Graduate Student Research Fund (~1,500 USD)

2017: Animal Behaviour Society (ABS) Developing Nations Award (~ \$2,500 USD)

**2016**: Rufford Small Grants for Nature Conservation (~ \$7,000 USD)

**2016 and 2014**: Ideawild equipment donation (Camera traps; ~ \$1800 USD)

2015: International Foundation of Science (IFS) Research Grant (~ \$12, 000 USD)

### **REFEREES**

Associate Professor Hazel Chapman

School of Biological Sciences, University of Canterbury, New Zealand

Email: hazel.chapman@canterbury.ac.nz

Phone No.+6433322058

Dr. Barshep Yahkat

Scientific Director, A. P. Leventis Ornithological Research Institute (APLORI),

Jos-East, Nigeria.

Email: yahkat.barshep@aplori.org

Phone No. +2348068976410

Professor Will Cresswell

School of Biology, University of St. Andrews, Fife, UK

Email: wrlc@st-andrews.ac.uk Phone No. +44 (0) 1334463010